（ギャモン）骨折り損の
くたびれ儲けってヤツだぜ！
This was a fool's errand! A total waste of time!
とっとと帰って　稼がねえとな。
チェッ。
Gotta get back to Japan and make some cash.
（ノノハ）あれ？　軸川先輩は？
Huh? Where's Jikugawa?
（キュービック）用事があるから
先に日本へ帰ってて　だって。
He said he had something to do and that we should head back to Japan without him.
ふ～ん。
（カイト）俺は　帰らない。
（一同）えっ？！
I'm not going back.
ルークが　何で変わっちまったのかを
確かめるまでは。
I have to find out why Rook changed so much.
（ギャモン）
だったら　てめえ１人で残りな。
Then you can stay by yourself.
これ以上　振り回されるのは
ごめんだぜ。
I've been toyed with enough.
（アナ）アナが思うに…
離れた方が　絵は全部見えるよ。
I think... from a distance, you can see the big picture more clearly.
アナの言うとおりだよ。
Ana's right.
離れてみれば分かることも
あるかもしれないし…。
There may be things you'll only understand once you're away from here.
きっと会えるよ。　カイトとルーク君は
パズルでつながってるんでしょう？
I'm sure you'll meet again. You're both connected by puzzles.
（ルーク）やはり　僕たちは
パズルでつながっている。
We are connected by puzzles.
カイトと…　僕…　それ以外　必要ない。
Kaito and I... There's no need for anything else.
（ビショップ）お呼びでしょうか　ルーク様。
You summoned me, Sir Rook?
「断罪の迷宮」の使用を許可する。
I authorize the use of the Labyrinth of Beheading.
あの禁じられたパズルを？
I thought that puzzle was banned...
かしこまりました。
As you command.
kimi no nounai he shinnyuu nemutteiru sukima ni
I infiltrate your brain while you're sleeping.
Baby, open the gate!
fukuzatsu sugi sekyuriti kakusareru to abakitaku naru
The security's too tough, but I want to expose what's hidden.
barabara ni chirabatteiru pasuwado wo hiroi atsume
I gather the pieces of the shattered password.
kakushin ni sematte iku sono shoutai wo misete
I get close to the core. Show me who you really are!
kantan ni kuria dekinai saki nante motto yomenai
I can't clear it easily. I can't even see what lies ahead.
kaidoku fukanou sumairu kikenna pazuru
Your indecipherable smile is a hazardous puzzle.
rokku sareta doa aru nara zutto tataite miru beki kazana hiraku wa
When you see a locked door, you should just hit it until a crack opens.
eien ni hodokenai nazo nanka wa nai
There's no mystery that lasts forever!
makiokosu, it's a supernova
I made it, it's a supernova!
tobikiri shigekitekina hirameki wo agemashou
Let's flash so bright it'd hurt!
Misskey-Misskey La-Tu-Ma
yume no naka it's a supernova
In my dreams, it's a supernova!
watashi wa sou brain diver
Yeah, I'm the brain diver!
kimi ga sagashi motometeru kotae ni nareru made
Until I can find the answer you're looking for...
Brain diver!
Labyrinth of Beheading
うわ～っ！　青が真っ青！
It's so blue!
ベネチア観光なんて　夢みた～い！
夢みた～い！
Sightseeing in Venice is like a dream come true!
It's a dream come true!
あっ！　欲しい？　ノノハスイーツ。
Want some Nonoha sweets?
No!
要らねえよ！　大体　なんで
ついてきたんだ　お前ら？！
First of all, why am I even here?
ギャモン君と一緒なら　海外で
ウロウロしても　安心だなって思って。
I thought that hanging around overseas would be safer if you were here!
えっ。
あと　イタリアって
おいしいもの　いっぱいでしょう！
And Italy has so many delicacies!
Maybe even Kaito and Cubie will cheer up after some fine dining.
そういうの　食べたら　カイトも
キューちゃんも　元気　出るかなって。
チェッ。
I think... this place isn't only about its beauty!
アナが思うに
美しいだけじゃないぞ！
イタリアは　レオレオのふるさとだし…。
ん？！　ダビンチ？　ああ　そうか！
Italy was the birthplace of Leo-Leo!
You mean Da Vinci? I see!
ミケリャンも～　ガリガリも～。
Miche-ryan too! And Gali-Gali too!
ミケランジェロに　ガリレオもか！
おいしいし　すごいよね！
Michelangelo and Galileo, right?
It's really more than just good food!
そういえば　ギャモン君の称号って
なんで　ガリレオなの？
Now that you mention it, why is your title Galileo, Gammon?
どうでもいいだろう　んなこたぁ！
Who cares about that?
チェッ　なんで　こんなことに…。
しかたないじゃない。　だって…。
Why did it have to come to this...?
We had no choice! Remember...
忘れないよ　オカベ君。
I'll never forget you, my beloved Okabe.
≫みんな～！　待ってくれ！
Guys! Wait!
軸川先輩？！
あぁ…　はぁ　はっ！
Jikugawa!
飛行機に乗っちゃ　ダメだ！
（一同）えっ？！
You can't get on the plane.
The one-way flight to Japan is already under POG control.
日本への直行便は　すでにＰＯＧに
押さえられているらしい。
雲の上を飛ぶ　罠だらけの飛行機…
逃げ場のない死のパズルだ！
A plane above the clouds, full of traps...
It's a deadly puzzle with no chance of escape!
なにっ？！
よく　そんなことが分かったな。
What?!
You're very well informed.
独自の情報網があるからね。
I have my own little information network.
学園長に帰国ルートを
変更してもらった。
I asked the principal to change your return route.
これが　新しい航空券だ。
These are your new tickets.
観光でもして　ゆっくりと
羽を伸ばしてくれ。
Go sightseeing if you want, enjoy yourselves.
で　ベネチアね…。
And so... we're in Venice.
ギャモンたち　よく船なんか
乗れるよね。
The other must be brave to get on those ships.
I'd get seasick right away. How about you, Kaito?
僕　すぐ酔っちゃうからさ。
ねぇ　カイト。
…ったく…　予定狂うぜ。
Dammit. My plans always get screwed up.
あっ！　ごはん！
うわ～！　おいしそう！
Oh, food!
It looks so delicious!
おなか　すいた！
そういや　俺も　腹減ったな。
Now I'm hungry!
Now that you mention it, I'm hungry too.
２人で　飯買ってきてくれよ。
いいよ　任せて！
Could you two go buy some food?
Sure, leave it to us!
がっつりしたの　頼むぜ！
Get me a lot, okay?
行こう！　アナ。
うん。
Let's go, Ana.
よろしくな。
ピザに　パニーニね！
Thanks!
Pizza and panini, right?
お待たせ～！
う～ん？！
Sorry for the wait!
あれ？　ギャモン君？
Huh? Where is Gammon?
It was here, right?
ここじゃ　なかったっけ？
ぼちぼち　おっ始めるか。
Shall we get started?
（ダイスマン）
あらららら　気づいてたの？
Oh my, you realized?
航空券に　ゴンドラの手配…
段取りがよすぎて　バレバレだぜ。
A sudden change in plane tickets and a gondola ride.
It was all too clean, obviously a trap.
大体よ…　あいつは
リンゴジュースしか　飲まねえからな。
First of all...
That guy only drinks apple juice.
ハッハ～！　お見事！　やるじゃ～ん！
Well done! You're not bad.
僕の変装を見抜くなんてさぁ！
There are not many who can see through my disguises.
ああ　でも困った。　命令は「ガリレオ
ダビンチ　エジソンをパズルに導け！」→
But this is bad.
My orders were to lead Galileo, Edison and Da Vinci to the puzzle.
だったのにさ。
あいつらは　必要ねえよ。
There's no need for them.
てめえらのパズルなんざ
俺１人で　十分だ。
I alone am more than enough to solve your puzzles.
へぇ～　面白いね　君。
（スイッチを押す音）
You're fascinating.
（ルーク）ようこそ　ＰＯＧへ。
ニュートン君…。
Welcome to the POG, Newton.
いや　ギヴァー・ミノタウロス…　かな？
（ソウジ）ソウジ君で結構です。
Or rather, the Giver, Minotaur?
Just call me Soji.
掛けたまえ。
Have a seat.
貴重な　お時間を割いていただき
感謝します。　クロスフィールド管理官。
Thank you for sparing me some of your expensive time, Chief Crossfield.
解道バロン　彼の頼みだ。
Kaido Baron requested it.
僕に聞きたいことがあると？
ええ…。
I hear you have some questions for me.
Yes. Regarding the Phi Brain plan.
「ファイ・ブレイン計画」について　少々。
ああ　どうやって
最重要機密を知ったのかは→
Oh, but let's not go into the details of how I know about something that's top secret.
詮索しない方向で　ひとつ。
ならば　分かるだろう。
Then you must understand I can't tell you anything about something that's top secret.
最重要機密について
話せることなどない。
Call in progress
（ビショップ）
「ルーク様　ガリレオが到着しました」。
Sir Rook, Galileo has arrived.
Call in progress
Gammon!
ギャモン君！
（ダイスマン）すんませ～ん。
作戦失敗っす。
I'm sorry. The plan failed.
（ビショップ）
彼の方が　上手だったようですね。
It seems he was on the offensive.
てめえか。
ようこそ　逆之上ギャモンさん。
Oh, it's you?
Welcome, Mr. Sakanoue Gammon.
あぁ。
いまだ　生きて出てきた者のない→
This is a puzzle that no one has left alive:
a fools' puzzle, the Labyrinth of Beheading.
愚者のパズル「断罪の迷宮」へ。
けっ！　どんなパズルだろうが
この俺様が　解放してやるぜ！
No matter what puzzle it is, I can solve it.
残念ながら
あなたには無理でしょう。
Unfortunately, that is not possible for you.
ああっ？！
可能性があるとすれば→
It is reserved for the bearer of the Armband of Orpheus, Daimon Kaito.
オルペウスの腕輪を持つ大門カイト
ただ１人。
また　あいつかよ。
（ビショップ）皮肉なものです。
Him again?
How ironic it would be
ガリレオの称号を持つあなたが
ガリレオとゆかりの深いこの地で→
if you, the bearer of title of Galileo, were to die in this land,
in which he is so deeply connected to.
命を終えるとは…。
とっとと始めようぜ！
Just get started already!
御託を聞かされたって　１円の
稼ぎにもなりゃしねえんだからよ。
I can't make any money from listening to your crap!
かしこまりました。
As you wish.
Gammon...? But they were supposed to go straight back to Japan!
ギャモン君…　日本への直行便に
乗ったはずじゃ…。　あっ？！
I guess you won't tell me anything.
話せることなどない…　ですか？
まあ　そう固いこと
おっしゃらずに…。
Don't say something so harsh.
こうしませんか　管理官。
僕が　チェスに勝ったら→
How about this instead?
If I can defeat you in chess, you answer just one of my questions.
一つだけ質問に答えていただく…
というのは？
君は何を賭ける？
And what will you wager?
How about...
では…→
一番大事なものを。
...what's most important to me.
フフッ。　いいだろう。
Very well.
（ビショップ）５つの水門　すべてを
通過することができれば→
There are five gates. The puzzle is solved by passing through all five of them.
このパズルは解放されます。
ゴンドラは　前進のみ可能。
The gondola can only go forward.
曲がることができるのは
曲線の水路のみ。
It can only turn in curved waterways.
直角に曲がることはできません。
It cannot turn in right-angled corners.
こんな狭い水路じゃあな。
The waterways are narrow.
水門を１つ　くぐるごとに
そのエリアのマップと→
Once you pass a gate,
the map of the next area and the time until the next gate closes will be sent to you.
次の水門が閉まるまでの時間が
データ転送されます。
水門は１番～５番まで　順番に
通過しなければなりません。
You must pass the gates in numerical order.
制限時間がゼロになると
水門は閉鎖。
If time runs out, the gate closes.
同時に　ゴンドラの補助動力が作動。
Also, the auxiliary engines will start.
水門へ向かって加速し…→
Accelerating towards the gate...
死をもって
あなたは知るでしょう。
And I believe you understand that means your death.
自分が太陽を引き立てるための
クズ星の１つにすぎなかった事を。
You are just a lowly star used to help the Sun.
ヘェ。
だったら　俺も教えてやるよ。
Then let me tell you something.
月も太陽も　俺様を中心に
回ってるって事をな！
The Sun and the Moon both orbit around me!
では　お先にどうぞ。
Well then, please do begin.
君は　ルールを知っているのかい？
Do you know the rules?
先攻である白は　目下　あるいは
実力が劣るほうが取るもの…→
The weaker or the junior makes the first move with the white.
ですよね。
ほら　僕のほうが　年上ですから。
I'm the older, after all.
なるほど…　では…。
I see. In that case...
もう！　ホテル　どこよ？！
Darn it, where is the hotel?
これも全部　ギャモン君が
私たちを置き去りにするから。
This is all because Gammon left us behind!
Look, Gali-Gali!
（ギャモン）直進すりゃ
心の声
２つ目の水門は　目の前だが…→
If I go straight ahead, I'll get to the second gate.
ハッ　そんな簡単な罠に
引っかかる俺様じゃねえ！
But I'm not gonna fall for that simple trap!
こっちが　正解のルートだ！
This is the right way!
ほう！
見えないな～。
I can't see him.
There!
うらぁ～～！
ギャモン君？！
Gammon!
あぁ？　近寄るな！
こいつは　愚者のパズルだ！
Don't interfere! This is a fools' puzzle!
This is bad!
大変！
けっ！
[TEL]カイト！
ん～？
ギャモン君が　愚者のパズルに！
Kaito!
Gammon is in a fools' puzzle!
うん。　何だと？！
What?!
「人として得た多くのものを
捨てねばならない」。
People must often throw away much of what they gained.
それが　ファイ・ブレインに到達する条件…
でしたよね。
That was a condition of achieving the Phi Brain, right?
捨てねばならないもの…
過去や感情　そして　友達。
Throw away your past, your feelings. And your friends.
すべては　ファイ・ブレイン完成のため…
と思っていたのですが→
I thought it was all for the completion of the Phi Brain,
殺す必要　あるんでしょうかね？
but is it necessary to kill them?
質問は　勝ってからのはずだが…。
I thought you were going to ask your question after you won.
あっ　これ　独り言ですから。
Oh, I'm just talking to myself.
（ギャモン）
やっぱり。　最短ルートを通ってたら
手詰まりになるところだったぜ。
I knew it.
If I had passed through with the quickest route, I would've gotten stuck.
He's charging ahead without hesitation.
迷わず進んでますね。
さすがは　ガリレオ。
He is Galileo, after all.
けっ！　何やってんだ？　俺は…。
What am I doing? This isn't like me.
らしくねえぜ！
（バロン）パズル選手権
優勝おめでとうございます。
Congratulations on your puzzle championship victory, Sakanoue Gammon.
逆之上ギャモン君。
うれしく思いますよ。
I am happy that I can welcome an outstanding student like yourself to the Root Academy.
君のような優秀な生徒を
√学園に迎えることができて。
勘違いすんなよ。　俺が　パズルを
解くのは　金のため　俺のためだ。
Don't get me wrong. I only solve puzzles for money. For myself!
大いに結構。
あっ？
More than enough.
強靭な意志で　パズルに挑み
答えに突き進むその姿は→
The way you challenge puzzles without hesitation and get straight to the answer
かの偉人を彷彿とさせます。
would put many great people to shame.
逆之上ギャモン君
君に　ガリレオの称号を贈りたい。
Sakanoue Gammon, I would like to give you the title of Galileo.
心の声
金以外は　どうでもよかった俺が→
I didn't care about anything but cash,
こんな　１円にもならねえパズルを
やってるなんてよ。
and yet here I am solving this crappy puzzle with no reward!
心の声
あいつのせいだ。　あいつが　パズルを
解くたびに　ムカつくなんてよ。
It's his fault. The way he solves puzzles pisses me off.
This isn't like me, god dammit!
らしくねえぜ！　まったくよ！
Galileo passed the third gate.
（ビショップ）
「ガリレオが　第３ゲートを通過しました」。
次々と　死のパズルに導かれる
カイト君の友達。
Kaito's friends are led to deadly puzzles one after another.
そこに何か　他の意図が
あるんじゃないだろうか。
Could there be some reason behind that?
例えば…　そう…→
For example, maybe...
個人的感情とかね。
Personal emotions.
チェックです。
Check.
くそっ！　どこだ？　ギャモン！
Dammit, where are you, Gammon?!
This city is like a puzzle...
…ったく　パズルみたいな街だぜ！
あっ！　なんだ？　この水路の形…。
Why is the canal shaped like that?
あっ。　あはっ。
これで最後のエリアだ。
This is the last area.
あっ。　こ　こいつは…。
Wait, what?
キャスリング…。
Castling.
キングを守るルーク…　ですか？
A rook protecting the king, is it?
This is just my guess...
勝手な推測ですが…。
チェックだ。
Check.
ファイ・ブレインという知性の極地に
到達するには→
...but I think friendly competition is required to get to the peak of the Phi Brian.
仲間との切磋琢磨が不可欠。
チェックだ。
Check.
ダブルチェック？！
Double check.
心の声
自軍のキングを守っていたはずの
敵のルークが　僕のキングを狙っている。
The enemy rook that was supposed to protect his king is attacking mine!
Even if I manage to escape with the king...
心の声
ここから　僕のキングを
逃したとしても…。
不要だ。
あっ。
They're unneccessary. Friendly competition and your Section Phi are both unnecessary.
仲間との切磋琢磨も　君たち
セクションΦも　すべて不要だ。
チェッ　どうなってやがる？！
What's going on?
答えが　ねえだと？！
クソッ？！　ＰＯＧめ！
There's no answer?! You POG bastards!
ハッハー！　迷ってる　迷ってる！
He's lost! He's lost!
けっ　おいおい！　普通に走っても
ぶつかるじゃねえか！
Hey! No one said anything about obstacles along the way!
あっ？！　水位が上がってる。
The water levels are rising.
まさか？！　満ち潮のせいか！
Is it because of the high tide?
ギャモン君！
けっ　くそ～っ！
Gammon!
Dammit!
ギャモン！
Gammon!
通過した！
カイト…。
He got through.
Kaito.
何しに来やがった！
ああ？！
What are you doing here?!
失せな！　このパズルは　俺のもんだ。
Get lost! This puzzle is mine!
お前？！
早く降りろ！　時間が　ねえんだ！
You...
Get off already! I'm short on time.
Give that to me!
ちょっと　貸せ！
てめえ！　何しやがる！
Son of a bitch! What are you doing?!
これは…。
返せ。　邪魔すんな！
This...
Give it back. Outta my way.
このパズル　答えがねえ。
チェッ！
There is no answer!
How dare they go this far...
あいつら　そこまでして…。
ル～～～ク！
Rook!
カイト…。
Kaito!
Get off!
おい！　降りろ！
あっ！
水位…　水路の幅…。
The water levels... The width of the canals.
見えた…。
Got it.
おい！　こんな狭い所
回れるわけねえだろう！
There's no way we could turn in that narrow space!
心の声
満ち潮で　水位が上がって→
The water levels rose because of the high tide,
and the canals got wider so we could turn.
水路の幅が広がって
曲がることができた。
水位が上がるタイミング。
心の声
The timing of the tide...
旋回することで
心の声
パズルが解ける　唯一の　この場所。
This is the only place where a turn can solve the puzzle.
心の声
やつは一瞬で　そこまで
見抜いたっていうのか？
He saw through that in only a second?
第５ゲート。
だが　間に合わねぇ！
The fifth gate.
We won't make it!
うわっ！　えいっ！
（ビショップ）
まさか？！　断罪の迷宮を…。
Impossible! They solved the Labyrinth of Beheading.
ぶわっ！
カイト…　解きやがった。
Kaito... He solved it.
Just like that, Kaito. Well done.
そうだよ　カイト…　それでいい…。
カイト！
ハァ　ハァ！
Kaito!
大丈夫？　カイト。　しっかりして！
Are you all right, Kaito? Wake up!
アナ！　私のクッキー　まだ　ある？
うん。
Ana, do you have any of my cookies?
Yeah. Here.
はい。
うん。
Wake up, Kaito!
戻って！　カイト！
カイト！　ダ…　ダメ～！
Kaito!
It... didn't work!
ぐわ～っ！
パズルタイムは　おしまい。
さっさと起きて　日本に帰るの！
Puzzle time is over!
Wake up so we can get back to Japan!
あい。
ゲンコツと　ノノハスイーツって！
普通のやつなら　１００％死んでるぞ。
A punch to the face and Nonoha sweets!
That would kill a normal person for sure!
カイト…。
Kaito...
うっ　あの女…。
That bitch...
「ルーク！　べぇ。→
Rook!
お前に　何があったかは
知らねえ！。→
I don't know what happened to you...
なんで　ここまで
すんのかもな！」。
...or why you'd go this far!
だけど　そんなこと　どうでもいい。
But I don't care either.
来るんなら　俺に来い！　ルーク。
If you're coming, come to me, Rook.
約束したじゃねえか。　お前の
パズルは全部　俺が解くって…。
I promised I would solve all your puzzles!
あっ。
完敗です。　管理官。
I lost, Chief.
チェスには少し自信があったんですが
勉強になりました。
I was confident in my chess skills, but I learned a lot today.
また　お手合わせください。
それでは…。
I look forward to playing with you again.
If you'll excuse me...
ウフッ。
いやいや　とんでもない相手に
挑戦しちゃったもんだ。　あぁ。
I challenged a really tough opponent.
あれ？　ジュース…。
Huh? My juice...
まっ　いいか。　収穫は　あったしね。
Ah, whatever. It was worth it.
独占欲と嫉妬か…。
Possessiveness and envy.
彼もまた　人としてのすべてを
捨て切れてはいない。
He hasn't thrown away all of his humanity yet.
（ダイスマン）
ハッ　ハッ　ハー！　ぶざまだね。
Pathetic!
１人で解けるなんて
息巻いておいて→
You boasted you could solve it alone,
結局　大門カイトに
チェッ。
持っていかれてんじゃん。
but in the end, Daimon Kaito did.
死なずに済んだことを
彼に感謝するんだね　ガリレオ。
Be grateful that he saved your ass, Galileo.
いや　クズ星君。　ハッ。
Or should I say, lowly star.
コケに　しやがって。
How dare he make fun of me...
I'll show them!
思い知らせてやるぜ！
月にも太陽にも！
I'll show the Sun and the Moon!
すべてのパズルは　俺様を中心に
回ってるってことをな！
All puzzles orbit around me!
tsukue no ue de umareta sekai
This world born on my table.
ichiban saki ni kimi ni misetakatta
I wanted you to see it first.
karappo no heya sotto nukedashite hashiri hajimeteta
I sneaked out of the empty room and started to run.
iki hazamasete oka wo noboru to
As I got to the top of the hill, out of breath,
kimi ga saki ni tsuite matteita ne
you were already there waiting for me.
takusan no hajimete kimi to mitsuketa takaramono datta
It was the first of many treasures we would find together.
kanashisa de afureta toki wa
When sorrow was overflowing in me,
nanimo iwazu ni tada soba ni ite kureta ne
you just silently stayed by my side.
ima de mo wasurenai yo
I still haven't forgotten that.
mata aou ne yakusoku wo shiyou
Let's promise we'll meet again.
kie wa shinai ano hi no sayonara
The goodbye of that day we'll never forget.
boku no subete kimi ga kureta michi
All I have I got from you,
zutto kokoro no naka hikaru yo
and it will all shine in my heart forever.